Hi I&#39;m Gautam Kaul. https://youtu.be/QvXBDmGBIjY
Xin chào, tôi là 39 Gautam Kaul https://youtu.be/QvXBDmGBIjY Tôi đến từ trường đại học Kinh Doanh ở bang Michigan, rất vui vì đề nghị
the X series on edX on corporate finance.
của chương trình X seri trên edX về tài chính doanh nghiệp.
&gt;&gt; Hi I&#39;m Amiyatosh Purnanandam.
Xin chào, tôi là Amiyatosh Purnanandam. 39
I&#39;m also at the Ross School of Business at the University of Michigan and
Tôi cũng tới từ trường đại học kinh doanh Michigan và 39
I&#39;ll be co-teaching this series with Gautam.
Tôi là đồng giảng viên chương trình này với Gautam
Gautam, I have a question for you.
Gautam, tôi có một câu hỏi
What fascinates you most about finance?
Điều gì về tài chính mà thu hút bạn nhất?
&gt;&gt; That&#39;s a great question.
Đây là một câu hỏi hay 39
I guess I&#39;ve always thought there are a few things in life one cares about.
Theo tôi, trong số những điều  mà chúng ta quan tâm 39
The most important one is love.
Điều quan trọng nhất chính là tình cảm
And there are three or four other things, which I won&#39;t get into, but
Còn 3 hay 4 điều khác nữa, nhưng với tôi
to me finance would be a very close number two.
tài chính gần như là đứng thứ 2.
Because I see it everywhere maybe I&#39;m get too carried away but
Bơi vì tôi thấy nó ở khắp nơi, có thể tôi nói hơi quá nhưng
I blithely think the understanding of time,
Tôi vô tình nghĩ rằng sự hiểu biết về thời cơ,
uncertainty, decision making is everywhere all the time.
việc đưa ra các quyết định là ở mọi lúc mọi nơi.
And if you get the few principles of finance right, I think, and
Và nếu bạn nắm bắt được những nguyên tắc của tài chính
I&#39;m not talking about formulas or the mechanics of it,
Tôi không nói về các công thức hay mặt cơ học của nó, 39
just ways of thinking, it&#39;s so powerful that it kind of stays with you and
chỉ là về cách nhận thức, nó đem lại nhiều công hiệu cho bạn 39
you can almost think about any problem in life using that framing.
bạn hoàn toàn có thể giải quyết mọi vấn đề trong cuộc sống với những nền tảng đó.
&gt;&gt; So let me follow up that, that finance is love.
Theo đó, đối với tôi thì tài chính là tình yêu.
I mean the last thing I think about when I think about finance is love.
Điều cuối cùng tôi nghĩ thì tài chính là tình yêu
In fact, when I think about finance I think about money.
Trên thực tế, điều mà tôi nghĩ về tài chính là tiền bạc.
I think about these folks on Wall Street and very competitive markets.
Tôi nghĩ về những con người trên phố Wall và những thị trường cạnh tranh.
&gt;&gt; Yes.
Vâng.
&gt;&gt; Everybody is out there to get you.
Mỗi người ở đó đều muốn kiếm lời từ bạn.
&gt;&gt; Very competitive traders and firms and markets and regulators.
Những thương nhân, các công ty, thị trường, người điều hành cạnh tranh khốc liệt
&gt;&gt; Very true.
Đó là sự thật
My parallel when I think about finance.
Một điều nữa khi tôi nghĩ về tài chính
You&#39;re right, but I see finance as democracy.
tôi coi tài chính như vấn đề về dân chủ 39
I see markets as access to everybody and
Thi trường mở cửa cho tất cả mọi người và
yes, it&#39;s true, it&#39;s about money, but I think the principles can be
đó là tiền, nhưng tôi thấy nguyên tắc có thể
used to use any scarce resource as the basis evaluation.
sử dụng tất cả các nguồn tài nguyên khan hiếm như việc đánh giá cơ sở
So for example, I think you&#39;d know Becker started this whole
Ví dụ như Becker đã bắt đầu tất cả 39
wave of using time as the constraint and value.
cách thức về việc sử dụng thời gian như là sự hạn chế và giá trị.
So that&#39;s what appeals to me about finance is that I think it&#39;s underused.
Vì vậy điều khiến tôi suy nghĩ là việc nó không được tận dụng.
Why is it only on Wall Street.
Tại sao nó lại chỉ ở phố Wall
Why don&#39;t governments use finance the way it should be.
Tại sao không có chính phủ nào sử dụng tài chính theo cách nên làm 39
Why don&#39;t they have a clue about how to value stuff.
Tại sao họ không tìm cách khiến phế thải có giá trị hơn
You know pull out things from thin air.
Bạn biết việc tạo ra những điều kỳ tích chứ
I wish the president of America or
Tôi mong tổng thống Mỹ hoặc
our country knew finance, knew financial markets, knew how value works.
đất nước chúng ta biết về tài chính, thị trường tài chính và các giá trị được tạo ra như thế nào
That would be so much better than sitting in the corner worry about money.
Điều đó tốt hơn nhiều việc ngồi góc nhà và lo nghĩ về tiền bạc.
So that&#39;s what fascinates me.
Đó là điều thu hút tôi
I think you could value any asset, including nature,
Tôi nghĩ bạn có thể tạo ra được mọi tài sản, kể cả tự nhiên
using the same principles.
bằng cách sử dụng những nguyên tắc đó.
So it&#39;s not the dollar that, that&#39;s just the [INAUDIBLE].
Đó thì không phải là đô la, nó là
&gt;&gt; Year, true.
Đúng vậy
I&#39;ve always thought about, dollar is after all just accounting for what we have done.
Tôi chỉ nghĩ về đồ là sau tất cả khi tính toán những thứ chúng tôi kiếm được
So when I think about corporations, when I think about firms, and
Khi tôi nghĩ về sự liên kết, nghĩ về các công ty, và
I look at the balance sheet.
tôi xem bảng cân đối kế toán.
I look at the income statements.
Tôi xem báo cáo thu nhập
To me these numbers are simply after the fact once we have done certain things.
Với tôi những con số đơn giản thể hiện công sức mà chúng ta đã làm
We are keeping track of what we did.
Chúng ra giữ lại dấu vết những công việc đó
&gt;&gt; Yes.
Vâng
&gt;&gt; Right?
Phải chứ
But most fascinating thing of course, in finance and
Nhưng đương nhiên điều thu hút nhất ở tài chính và
in life, is how you make decisions.
trong cuộc sống đó là cách mà bạn đưa ra các quyết định
And how do you live with implications of the decisions you make.
Và cách mà chúng ta chấp nhận các kết quả đến từ những quyết định đó
So let me ask you a question on that.
Tôi muốn hỏi bạn một câu hỏi
When you think about valuation,
Khi mà bạn nghĩ tới giá trị
something that you&#39;re going to be teaching in the first two module of this program.
điều mà bạn học được ở hai chương đầu trong khóa học này
What are the core say two or three key insights?
Cái gì là cốt lõi, hai hay ba chìa khóa ẩn giấu?
It&#39;s that you would like our students to learn in the first two modules.
Đó là điều bạn muốn học sinh học được ở hai bài đầu
&gt;&gt; I think because of the framework that finance provides,
Tôi nghĩ bởi vì điều cốt lõi mà tài chính cung cấp
you can take that same framework to any level.
Bạn có thể nắm được những nguyên tắc như vậy ở bất kỳ trình độ nào
So in this series we are geared more towards people who will be working for
Ở trong chương trình này, chúng tôi hướng tới những người đi làm
an entity.
an entity.
&gt;&gt; Okay. &gt;&gt; Right,
Đúng
instead of worrying about their own investments.
Thay vì lo lắng về các khoản đầu tư của mình
So therefore, the two fascinating things,
Vì vậy, hai điều thu hút
which are common across, are the issue of time and uncertainty.
cái mà nổi trổi hơn cả, đó là vấn đề về thời cơ và sự không chắc chắn
And the reason is, every time you make a decision, you&#39;re standing at a point but
Lý do là, bất kỳ khi nào bạn đưa ra quyết định, bạn chỉ nhìn được từ một chiều nhưng
it&#39;s going to affect you in the future and you don&#39;t know what the future is like.
điều này lại ảnh hưởng tới cả tương lai và bạn lại không biết trước được về tương lai
That&#39;s why I make fun of accounting sometimes, it&#39;s about the past and
Đó là lý do đôi khi tôi cũng ngớ ngẩn với những tài khoản, đó là quá khứ
the past is gone.
và quá khứ thì đã trôi qua
So, the fascinating thing about finances is the study of timeline uncertainties.
Nên, điều hấp dẫn của tài chính đó là việc nghiên cứu về các mốc thời gian của những điều không chắc chắn
So, the first course assumes no answer.
Khóa học đầu tiên không đưa ra câu trả lời nào
Because it&#39;s very tough I think even for people who have done finance to kind of
Bởi vì nó khá khó khắn, tôi thậm chí nhớ tới những người đã làm tài chính hay
take all the complexity and not break it up into pieces like Legos,
cả người tạo ra những điều phức tạp và không phá vỡ nó như Legos,
and deal with them separately, and put them back together.
phần chia chúng ra rồi lại sáp nhập lại.
What we tend to do is, think about time alone which is difficult enough, and
Chúng ta có xu hướng nghĩ về thời gian một mình, điều mà rất khó khắn,
kind of incorporate the notion of time value of money in multiple contexts.
kind of incorporate the notion of time value of money in multiple contexts.
And here the context is the firm trying to make decisions.
Đây là lúc mà các công ty cố gắng để tạo ra các quyết định
The second course will then introduce uncertainty and revisit everything.
Khóa học thứ hai sẽ giới thiệu về sự không chắc chắn và dễ thay đổi của sự việc
So, let me ask you something.
Tôi sẽ hỏi bạn một chút
So, I will make unreasonable assumptions
Tôi sẽ đưa ra các giả định phi lý
even I do this because I believe nature is not unreasonable.
Tôi làm như thế vì tôi tin bản chất thì không thể nào phi lý được
Human’s kind of mess things up.
Con người khiến mọi thứ trở nên lộn xộn.
So, I&#39;m gonna assume that the markets work, everything is perfect, nobody lies,
Vì thế tôi sẽ giả sử rằng thị trường làm việc, mọi thứ đều hoàn hảo, không ai nói dối
nobody bad incentives.
không ai có động cơ xấu
The trade is very easy, there not much transaction cost so that you get what
Buôn bán đễ dàng, không có các chi phí giao dịch vì vậy bạn có được
financing all about in a pretty, beautiful world, pretty actually does exist.
các nguồn tài chính tồn tại ở điều kiện tuyệt vời
So, let me ask you some question.
Tôi sẽ đưa ra vài câu hỏi
Tell me the value of this, because I know you very well, you love the fact
Nói cho tôi về giá tri của chúng, bởi vì tôi nghĩ các bạn rất giỏi, các bạn thích thực tiễn
that we have a beautiful world, but then you also tell me the world is messed up.
rằng chúng ta có một thế giới tươi đẹp, nhưng rồi các bạn lại bảo tôi rằng thế giới bị xáo trộn
&gt;&gt; I&#39;m there, in fact, I&#39;ll take it from there, that what&#39;s love without pain?
Tôi sẽ bắt đầu từ đây, tình yêu không có đau đớn?
&gt;&gt; So I&#39;m here to provide some pain.
Tôi ở đây để reo tới sự dau khổ đây
&gt;&gt; [LAUGH] No, no,
không
no, you are here to explain why there is pain not provide the pain.
không, bạn ở đây để giải thích tại sao lại có những sự khổ đau chứ không phải là tạo ra chúng
&gt;&gt; After all love is about longterm investments and
Sau tất cả thì tình cảm là sự đầu tư dài hạn và
there are a lot of uncertainties and risks surrounding love, so I see your point.
có rất nhiều những điều không chắc chắn và nguy hiểm xung quanh tình cảm, tôi biết quan điểm của các bạn
But in my world, there are firms,
Trong thế giới của tôi, có những công ty,
and firms are run by people.
và công ty thì được vận hành bởi con người
People have incentives.
Con người thì đều có động cơ.
They might sometimes slack off.
They might sometimes slack off.
They might sometimes hide information from others,
Họ đôi khi giấu diếm những thông tin với người khác,
and when it comes to money just think about these what I&#39;ll call frictions.
và khi đến lúc có lợi nhuận thì họ chỉ quan tâm chúng, thứ mà tôi gọi là sự ma sát.
We&#39;ll put some names to these frictions, we&#39;ll call them information friction or
Chúng ta sẽ đặt tên cho những sự xích mích này, chúng ta gọi chúng là thông tin ma sát hay
we&#39;ll call them agency friction.
đại diện ma sát
But the point is, in your world where the world works smoothly,
Nhưng quan trọng là, trong thế giới của bạn nơi thế giới vận hành trôi chảy,
nobody lies, nobody cheats, nobody hides information.
không ai nói dối, lừa đảo, giấu diếm thông tin.
That is an ideal world to translate that into a world that we live in,
Đó là thế giới lý tưởng để mà chúng ta sống ở đó.
the real world.
thế giới thực sự.
You have to think about both love and the pain that comes with love.
Bạn phải suy nghĩ về cả tình yêu và nỗi đau.
And to value in the asset, in fact, you have to bring them together.
Và để tạo ra của cải, chúng phải được cùng kết hợp
That when you think about a positive NPV project, our bread and
Khi bạn nghĩ về một giá trị hiện tại thuần tích cực,  thu nhập
butter in finance, we essentially are trading off that love and pain.
ở trong tài chính, về bản chất chúng ta đều có chi phí cơ hội về tình cảm và nỗi đau.
That is the return more than the risk that I&#39;m taking, right?
Đó là sự hồi đáp hơn cả sự mạo hiểm mà ta nhận
In corporate finance, in my world, we&#39;ll expand on that, and
Trọng tài chính doanh nghiệp, chúng ta sẽ phát triển và
we talk about What should you be thinking about as a corporate manager,
chúng ta nói về Thứ mà bạn nên nghĩ về quản trị doanh nghiệp,
or as the CFO of the firm, when you are thinking about issues,
hoặc như giám đốc điều hành, khi bạn nghĩ tới các vấn đề,
such as how much equity should I raise?
như là tôi nên dùng bao nhiều vốn?
How should I fund my business?
Tôi nên gấy dựng sự nghiệp như nào?
Or, should I keep cash on my balance sheet or not?
hay tôi có nên giữ tiền mặt trong bảng cân đối kế toán không?
Should I pay dividends or not?
Tôi có nên trả tiền lãi không?
So to connect it to your world,
Vậy để kết nối chúng với cuộc sống bạn,
essentially the two modules that I&#39;ll be doing after you come in is introduce
tôi sẽ giới thiệu bản chất về hai mô đun mà tôi dùng
realistic real world frictions into the models that you will have taught by then.
sự ma sát thực tiễn cho tới những hình mẫu mà các bạn sẽ được dạy sau này
And in that world, think about the flip side of your argument.
và trong thế giới, nghĩ về các mặt trái đối lập
Or let me say it this way.
Nói cách khác.
That you will teach how to value,
Anh sẽ dạy cách dánh giá,
given the financial policy or keeping fixed the financial policy.
xem có nên đưa ra chính sách tài chính hay giữ nguyên chính sách cũ.
I&#39;ll flip it and say what financial policy will maximize value.
Tôi sẽ hỏi ngược lại rằng chính sách tài chính nào sẽ tăng giá trị lên cực đại.
And in your frictionless world, in fact, there will be no role for folks like me.
And in your frictionless world, in fact, there will be no role for folks like me.
You&#39;ll say that financial policies are not relevant for value.
Anh nói chính sách tài chính không liên quan đến giá trị.
&gt;&gt; True.
Đúng vậy.
&gt;&gt; In your world in fact you&#39;ll say that whether the firm has more debt or equity,
Trong lĩnh vực của anh, anh bảo dù công ty đó có nợ hay vốn sở hữu nhiều hơn,
whether the firm has more cash or less cash, that will not affect its value.
undefined
But in a friction filled world those decisions will impact your value.
Nhưng trong thế giới tác động qua lại thì những quyết định đó sẽ ảnh hưởng đến giá trị.
So what I&#39;m hoping our students will get from the third and
Nên tôi hi vọng rằng trong bài học thứ ba và thứ tư
fourth module to think about maximizing firm value in real world.
sinh viên sẽ tính đến việc tăng giá trị tối ưu cho công ty trong thực tế.
So on that note, let me come back to you with this question.
Nhân tiện đây, tôi xin quay lại câu hỏi sau.
That when you think about the time value of money.
Rằng khi anh tính đến giá trị thời gian của đồng tiền.
And often, we think in terms of look,
Thường thì ta suy nghĩ về cách nhìn nhận,
a dollar today is better than a dollar tomorrow.
rằng giá trị của một đola hôm nay cao hơn ngày mai.
What do you think of the philosophical underpinning of that issue?
Anh nghĩ sao về cơ sở triết lý của việc đó?
&gt;&gt; I think the philosophical underpinning, which unfortunately,
Tôi nghĩ cơ sở triết lý đó rất quan trọng,
we probably won&#39;t spend much time on in this series, is everything to me.
tiếc là ta không giành nhiều thời gian để nói về nó.
It&#39;s basically we are impatient.
Căn bản là ta thiếu kiên nhân.
And, it&#39;s kind of, we presume that the interest rate is positive,
Và ta giả định rằng tỉ suất lãi là khả quan,
therefore we act.
nên ta hành động
But we, the fact that the interest rate is positive is because of our own
Nhưng thật ra tỉ suất lãi khả quan là do
preferences and behavior.
sự ưu tiên và hành vi của chúng ta.
That&#39;s what I find fascinating.
Điều đó khiến tôi rất hứng thú.
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
Phải.
&gt;&gt; And to me, that&#39;s a theory of interest, we both have read Fisher.
Đối với tôi, đó là giả định của lãi suất, chúng ta đều đã học cuốn Fisher rồi.
I think it&#39;s the most fascinating question.
Tôi nghĩ đó là câu hói rất thú vị.
The only unfortunate part about the series is we will not spend too much time.
Kém may ở đây là chúng ta không dành nhiều thời gian cho nó trong bộ bài giảng.
We will presume there is an interest rate, and we won&#39;t go too much into that.
Chúng ta sẽ giả định là có tỉ suất lãi, nhưng ta sẽ không đi sâu vào.
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
Phải.
&gt;&gt; To me actually I wish I could just do a course on that.
Tôi rất muốn làm một khóa về việc đó.
Or teach using theory of interest as the background.
Hoặc dạy lý thuyết về lãi suất làm nền tảng.
But let me go back to you for a second.
Nhưng để tôi quay lại một chút.
What is the role of markets in all of this?
Vai trò của thị trường là gì?
Remember, because when you asked me about love and finance and
Vì anh hỏi tôi về tình yêu và tài chính.
I think the reason I really like finance is it&#39;s market I said democracy.
Tôi nghĩ lý do tôi thích tài chính là vì thị trường, tôi đã nói là nền dân chủ.
And when I was thinking democracy, I was thinking people.
Khi tôi nghĩ về nền dân chủ, tôi nghĩ về con người.
When I was thinking people, I was thinking markets.
Khi tôi nghĩ về con người, tôi nghĩ đến thị trường.
When I was thinking democracy, I was thinking worthy.
Khi tôi nghĩ về nền dân chủ, tôi nghĩ đến những nhân vật quan trọng.
So the fact that you can vote and put your money where your mouth is, or
Nên việc anh có thể bầu và đầu tư tài chính hay bất cứ cái gì,
whatever the, is what&#39;s so powerful about markets.
đó là sức mạnh của thị trường.
And of what attracts me so much about it.
Đó cũng là thứ thu hút tôi rất nhiều.
So how will that fit?
Vậy nó vận hành thế nào?
It plays a very important role in how we go from me to you or you to me.
It plays a very important role in how we go from me to you or you to me.
You know what I mean?
Anh hiểu ý tôi chứ?
&gt;&gt; That&#39;s the connector between these two modules right?
Đó cũng là cầu nối giữa hai khóa học này.
In fact corporate finance is nothing without markets.
Tài chính doanh nghiệp sẽ chẳng là gì nếu thiếu thị trường.
When you you think about corporate finance, and you&#39;re thinking about
Khi anh nghĩ đến tài chính thị trường, và anh đang nghĩ đến
private companies or you&#39;re thinking about public traded companies.
các công ty tư nhân hay các công ty cổ phần đại chúng.
The key distinction that you make from, say, household finance,
Điểm phân biệt mấu chốt là anh lấy từ đâu, ví dụ như tài chính gia đình,
when I&#39;m thinking about my own pocketbook or my own budget, is that for
khi tôi nghĩ về ngân quỹ của cá nhân tôi,
corporations there&#39;s a marketplace out there.
với các tập đoàn lớn, thị trường là ở ngoài kia.
A stock market, a bond market, a derivative market,
Có thị trường chứng khoán, thị trường trái phiếu, thị trường chứng khoán phái sinh,
where the pricing happens.
việc định giá xảy ra ở đâu.
And when firms are making decision, when they&#39;re investing,
Khi các công ty ra quyết định khi nào thì đầu tư,
what they are thinking is that, well if I invest $100 today.
Điều mà họ hướng tới là "Nếu tôi đầu tư 100 đôla.
I raise that money.
"Tôi sẽ phải làm ra tiền."
&gt;From where?
"Từ dâu?"
&gt;From the markets.
"Từ các thị trường."
So the market is giving me $100 and they&#39;re expecting some return right?
Vậy thị trường cho tôi 100 đôla và họ cũng mong có tiền đúng không?
So my decision whether I should invest $100 or not fundamentally depends
Vậy nên quyết định có nên đầu tư 100 đôla của tôi phụ thuộc vào
on what is the expectation of return by the providers of capital to my firm?
mức sinh lời các cổ đông mong đợi.
So in corporate finance we take that as given.
Trong tài chính doanh nghiệp thì điều đó luôn đúng.
Now the market gives me the hurdle rate.
Thị trường cho tôi mức sinh lời tối thiểu.
Market tells me as the CFO for this kind of project you must earn 10% return.
Thị trường bảo với tư cách là giám đốc tài chính của dự án tôi phải kiếm được 10% mức sinh lời.
And inside the firm I have to work hard
Tôi phải cố gắng
to beat that 10% hurdle rate to create a positive NPV project.
để vượt qua 10% mức sinh lời tối thiểu, tạo ra dự án có giá trị hiện tại thuần khả quan.
So if you take markets away from corporate finance, we are essentially like
Nếu tài chính doanh nghiệp không có thị trường,
directionless in a sense that we don&#39;t know what my hurdle rate will be, okay?
thì ta sẽ mất phương hướng do không biết được mức sinh lời tối thiểu.
But it get&#39;s more exciting,
Nhưng việc biết được mức sinh lời tối thiểu
more fascinating beyond just getting the hurdle rate so
kém thú vị nhiều lần
that we can compute positive, whether the product is positive NPV or not.
so với việc ta có thể tính toán sản phẩm có giá trị hiện tại thuần khả quan hay không.
Marketplace is where we have a voice as a shareholder, as investors.
Thị trường là nơi ta có tiếng nói với tư cách là cổ đông, là nhà đầu tư.
So in democracy we vote, in markets we vote with our feet.
Trong nền dân chủ, ta đi bầu. Trong thị trường, ta tự bầu cho chính mình.
If I don&#39;t like your company&#39;s policies, I don&#39;t like your share price, I sell.
Nếu tôi không thích chính sách công ty anh, tôi không thích giá cổ phiếu của anh, thì tôi bán.
I get out, and that&#39;s a very powerful vote.
Tôi xin rút, đó là một lá phiếu quyền lực.
When I sell, and
Khi tôi bán,
your stock price goes down, your cost of capital goes up, effectively.
giá cổ phiếu của anh giảm, tỉ suất lãi tăng.
Which means your hurdle rate goes up, which means the next you project that you
Nghĩa là mức sinh lời tối thiểu của anh tăng, nghĩa là trong dự án tiếp theo
do you have to now think hard what you did that markets did not like.
anh phải suy nghĩ kĩ xem anh đã làm gì khiến thị trường không hứng thú.
So in a sense connecting to your thought about market being democracy.
Bằng cách liên tưởng thị trường là nền dân chủ.
I think it&#39;s the most powerful democracy that you can have.
Tôi nghĩ đó là một nền dân chủ quyền lực nhất mà anh có được.
Because you don&#39;t have to wait for
Vì anh không phải đợi
a five yearly election, election after every four years.
cuộc bầu cử cách nhau bốn, năm năm.
You can vote every nanosecond thanks to high frequency trading in the marketplace.
Anh có thể bầu trong mọi thời khắc nhờ vào sự giao thương liên tục trong thị trường.
So that&#39;s one.
Đó là một khía cạnh.
But the second aspect, where corporate finance and markets, get integrated
Khía cạnh thứ hai, nơi mà tài chính doanh nghiệp và thị trường sát nhập với nhau
is about one of the fundamental things about finance that I love the most.
đó là một trong những điểm mấu chốt ở tài chính mà tôi thích nhất.
That finance is the field where, when I came for
Đó cũng chính là lĩnh vực
my PhD, I thought I&#39;m going to learn to measure markets.
tôi chọn để học Tiến sĩ, tôi đã nghĩ tôi sẽ học để đo lường thị trường.
I thought I&#39;m going to learn about dividend pricing.
Tôi nghĩ tôi sẽ học về cổ tức.
I thought I&#39;m going to learn about risk management.
Học về quản trị rủi ro.
Quickly I realized that essentially what I&#39;m
Tôi nhanh chóng nhận ra tôi sẽ học được
learning is all about market for information.
tất cả thông tin thị trường.
All about market for information.
Tất cả đều là thông tin thị trường.
So why do the stock prices move to begin with?
So why do the stock prices move to begin with?
Because you get some new information about the company,
Vì anh có thông tin mới về công ty.
about the macroeconomy, about the competitors.
về kinh tế vĩ mô, về các đối thủ cạnh tranh.
There&#39;s something that is relevant for the valuation of the fund that moves.
Có một thứ gì đó liên quan đến việc định giá của nguồn quỹ lăn bánh.
If that information changes, so
Nếu thông tin đó thay đổi,
does the stock price of that company in the marketplace.
thì giá cổ phiếu của công ty đó trên thị trường cũng sẽ thay đổi.
So from a corporate finance perspective, from the market we get the hurdle rate.
Từ quan điểm tài chính doanh nghiệp, từ thị trường ta có được mức sinh lời tối thiểu,
And from the market we also get the information that is collectively
Từ thị trường, ta còn có thông tin chọn lọc
what the market is thinking about me as a firm.
rằng thị trường nghĩ thế nào về tôi với tư cách là một công ty.
And as a CFO it&#39;s a two-way transmitter going on.
Là giám đốc tài chính, có hai hướng truyền tải sẽ xảy ra.
CFO is releasing information that hey, I&#39;m going to do this project, this project,
Anh ta sẽ tung tin rằng tôi đang làm dự án này.
and that project.
và dự án kia.
And the market is telling we like your this project, this, and not this.
Và thị trường sẽ nói ta biết họ thích điểm nào, không thích điểm nào.
So, it&#39;s this fascinating two-way interaction or feedback or
Nên đây là cách tương tác hai chiều, phản hồi hai chiều,
whatever we want to call it that lies at the core of
ta gọi sao cũng được, nó là tâm điểm
an economy that functions based on free markets and
của một nền kinh tế vận hành dựa trên thị trường tự do
based on stock prices that form based on this information and expectation.
và dựa trên giá cổ phiếu hình thành dựa trên những thông tin và yêu cầu trên.
&gt;&gt; No, I completely agree.
Tôi hoàn toàn đồng ý.
Actually The one thing I find in this series which may,
Thật ra điều mà tôi nhận thấy
students may struggle with, the learners may struggle with is
trong bài giảng khiến người học gặp khó khăn
that we have to put, and you and I have talked about this,
là ta phải, anh và tôi đã bàn rồi,
we have to put market somewhere, because they&#39;re so fundamental.
ta phải đặt thị trường vào đâu đó, vì thị trường là nền tảng quá lớn.
So I feel the same way as you feel, there will be no corporate plans for
Nên tôi có cùng cảm nhận với anh, nếu không giảng về thị trường,
the market, I will feel like undervaluation of the market.
tôi sẽ cảm thấy ta đang đánh giá thấp nó.
Because all the pricing is coming from the marketplace.
Vì giá cả đều từ thị trường mà ra.
And I assume what it is.
Và tôi giả định.
And I assume the markets are perfect, and worth all the time.
Tôi giả định thị trường là hoàn hảo, và đáng giá trong mọi thời điểm.
So I get with that, but that&#39;s why I think markets always come first, in some sense.
Đó là lý do tôi nghĩ phải luôn ưu tiên thị trường.
&gt;&gt; Let me push back on that a little bit.
Cho tôi quay lại một chút.
Would you have a market without a firm?
Anh sẽ có thị trường mà không cần công ty chứ?
&gt;&gt; No.
Không.
&gt;&gt; Well, there you go.
Nó là thế đấy.
So, it&#39;s the chicken and egg story, right?
Giống như câu chuyện gà và quả trứng đúng không?
&gt;&gt; Yes, yes, yes.
&gt;&gt; Yes, yes, yes.
&gt;&gt; The reason I push back on that a little bit is because, in your world,
Lý do tôi quay lại là vì trong lĩnh vực của anh,
what you&#39;re doing is you&#39;re &gt;&gt; Pricing for impatience
anh đang định giá cho sự thiếu kiên nhẫn
and pricing for risk on top of that.
và trên hết là định giá rủi ro.
So you&#39;ll have a time value of money, and you have risk set on that cash loans,
Vậy nên anh sẽ giá trị thời gian của tiền tệ, và có rủi ro của tiền vay.
and you&#39;re going to teach our students how you do evaluations.
và anh sẽ dạy sinh viên cách anh đánh giá.
And corporations provide those securities in the marker,
Và các công ty cung cấp những chứng khoán này ra thị trường,
and investors, depending on their preferences and
và các nhàn đầu tư, tùy vào nguồn tham khảo
impatience are going to prize these securities.
và tính nôn nóng của họ sẽ định giá chứng khoán.
But let me change the topic a little bit, and let me ask you about
Nhưng để tôi lái qua chủ để này một chút và để tôi hỏi anh
something that we all have witnessed, in the last ten years,
về những sự kiện ta đều đã chứng kiến suốt 10 năm qua.
that there have been a lot of talks about breakdown in financial markets.
Có khá nhiều cuộc tranh luận về sự sụp đổ của thị trường tài chính.
I&#39;m thinking about Lehman Brothers failure.
Tôi đang nghĩ đến sự thất bại của ngân hàng Lehman Brothers.
I&#39;m thinking about mortgage crisis.
Tôi đang nghĩ đến khủng hoảng nhà đất.
And when those breakdowns happen, what do you think would
Khi những sự kiện đó xảy ra,
be the recommendation that he&#39;ll give to folks who are doing valuation?
thì lời khuyên anh đưa ra cho những người đang định giá chứng khoán là gì?
Because one of the things that I keep hearing, that hey,
Vì tôi cứ nghe người ta nói mãi
you are in 2008, 2009,- &gt;&gt; Mm-hm.
rằng anh đang nói về những năm 2008 và 2009.
&gt;&gt; I&#39;ve learned all these beautiful models, capital asset pricing models.
Tôi đã học hỏi những mô hình tài chính và mô hình định giá tài sản vốn rồi.
But sometimes they don&#39;t work.
Nhưng đôi lúc những cách đó không hiệu quả.
&gt;&gt; Yes.
Đúng vậy.
&gt;&gt; What&#39;s your part on that?
Anh nghĩ thế nào về quan điểm trên?
&gt;&gt; That&#39;s a great great point.
Đó cũng là một ý kiến hay.
I think clearly the way to be set up in my world,
Tôi nghĩ cách để giàu có trong lĩnh vực tài chính,
which is reflected in this particular context in the first two courses,
điều nãy cũng được phản ánh trong hai khóa học đầu tiên
is we don&#39;t even deal with those issues.
là chúng tôi không hề bận tâm đến những vấn đề đó.
So that&#39;s where I think the value of knowing the word with frictions and
Nên đó cũng là điểm mà tôi nghĩ giá trị của việc biết rõ sự tác động qua lại
within centers and conflicts of interest come into picture.
và việc hiểu về xung đội lợi ích trở nên dễ nắm bắt hơn.
&gt;&gt; I just wanted to corner you with that notion.
Tôi mong anh sẽ đổi hướng nghĩ theo cách đó.
&gt;&gt; No, no. &gt;&gt; That indeed in your world there will
Không, không. Công nhận là trong thế giới của anh
not be a financial crisis.
thì khủng hoảng tài chính không xảy ra.
&gt;&gt; That&#39;s a perfect world.
Đó là một thế giới hoàn hảo.
&gt;&gt; Right?
Đúng không?
&gt;&gt; So, in fact what would be interesting if our students see
Vậy thì đâu mới là điểm thú vị nếu sinh viên của ta
that when we introduce informational frictions
nhận thấy rằng ta giới thiệu về tác động thông tin
that that perfect market sometimes might fade a little, might delay.
rằng một thị trường hoàn hảo đôi lúc cũng bị mất một ít, trì trệ một ít.
&gt;&gt; Yes.
Đúng vậy.
&gt;&gt; One of the things that will be our students who learn in this cities is that.
Một trong những bài học cho sinh viên là
When you have serial informational frictions
khi bạn có một chuỗi tương tác thông tin
then you might end up in a situation where markets might not just work.
thì bạn vẫn có thể rơi vào tình huống không áp dụng cho thị trường được.
&gt;&gt; No it&#39;s like as I said, I mean the market democracy also has the danger
Không, như tôi đã nói, đôi lúc thị trường dân chủ cũng tồn tại mối nguy
of somebody hijacking it once in a while.
như việc ai đó cướp máy bay vậy.
[LAUGH] And it&#39;s happened in our own past.
Và nó đã từng xảy ra rồi.
We are both from India.
Chúng ta đều đến từ Ấn Độ.
It&#39;s happened in India,
Nó cũng đã xảy ra ở Ân Độ,
too, where a democratically elected person basically froze the market.
nơi mà thủ tướng đảng dân chủ làm thị trường đóng băng.
Same thing can happen, and I think that&#39;s the beauty of finance,
Điều tương tự có thể xảy ra, tôi nghĩ đó là điểm tốt của tài chính,
is that it doesn&#39;t stop at assuming.
đó là tài chính không dừng lại ở giả định.
It didn&#39;t stop at assuming the world as a perfect place.
Nó không dừng lại ở việc giả định thế giới này là hoàn hảo.
In fact I would say that in the last 40 years,
Tôi khẳng định rằng suốt 40 năm qua
most of the contributions of finance have been in the areas where
hầu hết những đóng góp của tài chính
we have begun to understand the real world much better using fundamentals.
đã giúp ta hiểu tốt hơn về thế giới thật bằng cách dùng những nguyên lý cơ bản.
The fundamentals were not in the first two decades of even option pricing.
The fundamentals were not in the first two decades of even option pricing.
The fundamental pricing models were there, but
Khuôn mẫu định giá cơ bản đã tồn tại,
they were also making too many perfect presumptions, as you and I know.
nhưng có quá nhiều giả định hoàn hảo.
So I really think that even this CD&#39;s If we had offered it 40 years ago,
So I really think that even this CD&#39;s If we had offered it 40 years ago,
we would have gotten away with just doing evaluation.
we would have gotten away with just doing evaluation.
And by the way, a lot of business schools got away with doing just that piece and
Có nhiều trường kinh doanh lách luật bằng cách đó
saying, financing is irrelevant.
và họ nói rằng tài chính không liên quan.
I think the beauty of this series is both you and I have gotten together,
Tôi nghĩ điểm mạnh của chuỗi bài giảng này là tôi và anh cùng đứng lớp.
we both know finance, but we also have our special interests and specialities.
Chúng ta đều hiểu rõ tài chính nhưng ta có sở thích và chuyên môn riêng.
What I think they use, hopefully, the user will take away, or the learner
Tôi mong rằng người học
will take away from this, is how finance also allows you to understand complexity.
sẽ tiếp thu được rằng tài chính cho phép ta hiểu sự phức tạp bằng cách nào.
And that&#39;s where I would say it&#39;s more economics than finance.
And that&#39;s where I would say it&#39;s more economics than finance.
I don&#39;t wanna get.
I don&#39;t wanna get.
The one time I get a little bit upset is when finance
Lần mà tôi buồn bực là khi tài chính
people think there&#39;s no mother discipline.
là khi mọi người nghĩ nó không có không có kỉ luật.
The mother discipline is economics,
Quy luật chính yếu ở đây là nền kinh tế,
that&#39;s where information economics started, and all that.
nơi mà nền kinh tế thông tin bắt đầu.
So the more we have embraced economics,
Ta càng coi trọng nền kinh tế
the better off finance has been as a discipline.
tài chính càng trở nên có quy tắc hơn.
In fact, the reason I like this course is that now folks who are working to
Tôi thích khóa học này là vì những người đang học
get an MBA or working at a company, they will not just see the perfect finance.
để lấy bằng MBA hoặc đang làm việc, họ không chỉ hiểu về tài chính.
They will see it with its complexities.
Họ còn hiểu về sự phức tạp cuả nó.
And hopefully, they will then be enticed and excited to do
Sau đó họ có thể bị lôi cuốn
deeper finance and even PhD, I mean, that&#39;s what&#39;s fascinating to me, right?
để học sâu hơn và học lên Tiến sĩ, đó là điều khiến tôi hứng thú.
That&#39;s why I&#39;d be introducing this course.
Đó cũng là lý do tôi giới thiệu khóa học.
&gt;&gt; Let me ask you a more personal question which is on my mind, and
Để tôi hỏi anh thêm vài câu về suy nghĩ của tôi
it&#39;s not related to finance so much as why did you agree to perform in this format?
không liên quan đến lý do anh giảng dạy.
&gt;&gt; The reach that you can have by just
&gt;&gt; The reach that you can have by just
having a classroom experience is going to be much smaller
having a classroom experience is going to be much smaller
than the reach that you can have with this kind of format, number one.
than the reach that you can have with this kind of format, number one.
And that is important to me
And that is important to me
because going back to our course, where we were talking about frictions and
because going back to our course, where we were talking about frictions and
that create a need for understanding corporate finance.
that create a need for understanding corporate finance.
And when removed frictions, value improves.
And when removed frictions, value improves.
So, similarly, if we remove or reduce frictions in education, the way
So, similarly, if we remove or reduce frictions in education, the way
folks get education, you can improve value for the society as a whole.
folks get education, you can improve value for the society as a whole.
And I actually believe that because
And I actually believe that because
the fundamental value to human development is education.
the fundamental value to human development is education.
If you look at last thousands and
If you look at last thousands and
thousands of years of the development of mankind, the fundamental breakthrough
thousands of years of the development of mankind, the fundamental breakthrough
that have happened when as a collectively as a society, or as human beings,
that have happened when as a collectively as a society, or as human beings,
we discover something new and we share that knowledge with everyone, right.
we discover something new and we share that knowledge with everyone, right.
And as we become smarter as human beings our
And as we become smarter as human beings our
ability to share those knowledge has also improved a lot, right.
ability to share those knowledge has also improved a lot, right.
And now I think we are at a time were
And now I think we are at a time were
I don&#39;t have to go to Brazil to teach a class in Corporate Finance.
I don&#39;t have to go to Brazil to teach a class in Corporate Finance.
I don&#39;t have to go to India physically to teach a class in Corporate Finance,
I don&#39;t have to go to India physically to teach a class in Corporate Finance,
I can do it, I can reach.
I can do it, I can reach.
That audience sitting here in Ann Arbor, which to me, is a lot of power in that.
That audience sitting here in Ann Arbor, which to me, is a lot of power in that.
&gt;&gt; You say it, now you&#39;ll understand why I think finance is love, and
&gt;&gt; You say it, now you&#39;ll understand why I think finance is love, and
the way we are teaching it.
the way we are teaching it.
One way to think about it is that the textbook idea of a strategy
One way to think about it is that the textbook idea of a strategy
Is that market&#39;s working all the time, and you can create positive NPV.
Is that market&#39;s working all the time, and you can create positive NPV.
I think if market&#39;s working all the time,
I think if market&#39;s working all the time,
[LAUGH] finding NPV positive projects would be really difficult.
[LAUGH] finding NPV positive projects would be really difficult.
So another way to think about it is,
So another way to think about it is,
removing frictions is the way to create value, right?
removing frictions is the way to create value, right?
And what&#39;s so nice is that this is what we are doing, too.
And what&#39;s so nice is that this is what we are doing, too.
&gt;&gt; Right.
&gt;&gt; Right.
&gt;&gt; We are creating a market. &gt;&gt; Yeah.
&gt;&gt; We are creating a market. &gt;&gt; Yeah.
&gt;&gt; Which is hopefully valuable to the learners and so on.
&gt;&gt; Which is hopefully valuable to the learners and so on.
&gt;&gt; Just to build on that, this city sets the stage for
&gt;&gt; Just to build on that, this city sets the stage for
understanding at a deeper level, the role of regulation, for example.
understanding at a deeper level, the role of regulation, for example.
Or the role of interventions by governments
Or the role of interventions by governments
across the financial markets.
across the financial markets.
And we have witnessed a lot of that in the recent years, be it from
And we have witnessed a lot of that in the recent years, be it from
the Federal Reserve Bank in the US, to the European Central Bank worldwide.
the Federal Reserve Bank in the US, to the European Central Bank worldwide.
And these policies that governments take, they have implications that go
And these policies that governments take, they have implications that go
far beyond the shareholders and bondholders of the firm.
far beyond the shareholders and bondholders of the firm.
&gt;&gt; Yes, it&#39;s societal, right?
&gt;&gt; Yes, it&#39;s societal, right?
&gt;&gt; It has the implication for the entire society.
&gt;&gt; It has the implication for the entire society.
And I would say, even when we think about society,
And I would say, even when we think about society,
it has implications for beyond what you think of society as of today.
it has implications for beyond what you think of society as of today.
&gt;&gt; That&#39;s true. &gt;&gt; It has implications for
&gt;&gt; That&#39;s true. &gt;&gt; It has implications for
society that will be tomorrow.
society that will be tomorrow.
And one of the failures of democracy sometimes is that when you have democracy,
And one of the failures of democracy sometimes is that when you have democracy,
the future generation does not have a vote.
the future generation does not have a vote.
&gt;&gt; They&#39;re not even here.
&gt;&gt; They&#39;re not even here.
People who are not yet born, they can&#39;t vote on a policy that might have,
People who are not yet born, they can&#39;t vote on a policy that might have,
perhaps, large impact on global warming.
perhaps, large impact on global warming.
Who is going to speak for them?
Who is going to speak for them?
Finance to me,
Finance to me,
comes across as a fundamental tool that has some hope to settle those issues.
comes across as a fundamental tool that has some hope to settle those issues.
&gt;&gt; I completely agree.
&gt;&gt; I completely agree.
&gt;&gt; Because in finance, we deal with issues about making decisions today for-
&gt;&gt; Because in finance, we deal with issues about making decisions today for-
&gt;&gt; A very long period.
&gt;&gt; A very long period.
&gt;&gt; Something tomorrow, for a long time period.
&gt;&gt; Something tomorrow, for a long time period.
So tools that we have in finance, you talked about interest rates.
So tools that we have in finance, you talked about interest rates.
You talked about price of risk.
You talked about price of risk.
In fact, we can use those tools to do, A, learn a little bit more in a very
In fact, we can use those tools to do, A, learn a little bit more in a very
fundamental manner how we should think about pricing these environmental risks.
fundamental manner how we should think about pricing these environmental risks.
How we should think about a marketplace for global warming.
How we should think about a marketplace for global warming.
And second, how we can use the information from that marketplace to
And second, how we can use the information from that marketplace to
regulate some of these behavior that perhaps we,
regulate some of these behavior that perhaps we,
collectively, as a society, are engaged in right now.
collectively, as a society, are engaged in right now.
&gt;&gt; So consistent with the whole structure of the series, in the first course,
&gt;&gt; So consistent with the whole structure of the series, in the first course,
I will deal simply with the notion of time value money.
I will deal simply with the notion of time value money.
But it will be done with a lot of applications, and
But it will be done with a lot of applications, and
the context will be a firm making a decision about a project evaluation.
the context will be a firm making a decision about a project evaluation.
The thing that I will not do is risk,
The thing that I will not do is risk,
and it&#39;s a pattern, I think, adopted across all top business schools,
and it&#39;s a pattern, I think, adopted across all top business schools,
is the reason is if you combine both, it becomes a bit much.
is the reason is if you combine both, it becomes a bit much.
And what I like about finance is you can take them like separate Lego pieces,
And what I like about finance is you can take them like separate Lego pieces,
get familiar, and then put them all together.
get familiar, and then put them all together.
The second course is all about risk.
The second course is all about risk.
And the fundamental notion is very simple but
And the fundamental notion is very simple but
very powerful, which is, that risk for whom?
very powerful, which is, that risk for whom?
It is for the people investing in your company, and we&#39;ll assume that those folks
It is for the people investing in your company, and we&#39;ll assume that those folks
are risk averse, which behavioral data shows they are.
are risk averse, which behavioral data shows they are.
And that simple fact will lead to what is called portfolio theory and
And that simple fact will lead to what is called portfolio theory and
the measure of risk, or beta.
the measure of risk, or beta.
And we spend one four week period trying to both understand the measure of risk,
And we spend one four week period trying to both understand the measure of risk,
apply it in the context of selecting projects.
apply it in the context of selecting projects.
So, folks, I&#39;ll see you in class,
So, folks, I&#39;ll see you in class,
starting with course one in then on to course two.
starting with course one in then on to course two.
Bye, now.
Bye, now.